Preliminary Guide to the Anne Firor Scott Papers, 1939-2003 RL.01155
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anne Firor Scott papers
1939-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Scott, Anne Firor, 1921-
RL.01155
19 Linear Feet
11,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
In addition, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Anne Firor Scott Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1985-2008.
Biographical Note
Professor emerita of history at Duke University, Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
The collection contains writings of Anne Firor Scott and materials relating to her academic work in Southern and women's history. The materials primarily refer to her scholarly activities, and include her dissertation, occasional papers, articles, speeches and lectures, book reviews, contracts, conference proceedings and schedules, course materials, newspaper clippings, and other activities related to academia. There is also a file of correspondence written by Anna Lord Strauss (then president of the League of Women Voters) in 1949 and mailed to all members the league. Notes by Scott in this file explain her connection to Strauss, and the circumstances of the correspondence. In addition, there are newspaper articles related to the first and second editions of Scott's book, The Southern Lady. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Preliminary container lists exist for only parts of the collection.
Women -- History; Duke University. Dept. of History -- Faculty; Women -- United States -- History; Women -- History -- Congresses; Women historians -- United States; Education, Higher -- North Carolina; History -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Southern States -- History; Duke University -- Faculty; Scott, Anne Firor, 1921-; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Strauss, Anna Lord, 1899-1979; Scott, Anne Firor, 1921-; League of Women Voters (U.S.)
- Accession (2000-0293)
  - box 1 (Box 1)
    - Final Lectures Over the Years, 1957-1992 (Box 1)
    - Teaching Introductory Course from Documents (Box 1)
    - Clippings
      - 1960s, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1970s (Box 1)
      - 1990s (Box 1)
    - Outside Lectures-Clippings, 1980s (Box 1)
  - box 2 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters Connection (correspondence included) (Box 2)
    - Notes for Class Discussion in Introductory Course (Box 2)
    - Reviews of Making the Invisible Woman Visible (Box 2)
- Accession (2000-0335)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Attention: The first folder contains restricted material. Contact Research Services.
  - box 1 (Box 1)
    - The Southern Lady 25th Anniversary Edition (Box 1)
      (RESTRICTED)
    - Speech and article for Virginia Foundation for the Humanities, 1983, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Article on William Bacon Evans, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Comments: Southern Association of Women Historians, 1988 Juneand OAH Panel, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Book review, Janet Browne, Charles Darwin: Voyaging, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Harvard paper on Veblen (Box 1)
    - Duke speeches, 1979, 1990, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous speeches, 1974-2000 (Box 1)
- Accession (2001-0120)
  Scope and Contents note
  Addition (2001-0120) (2 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1986-2001) includes two rolls of microfilm negatives containing Scott's diaries, dating 1986-2001 and 1987-2000.
- Accessions (2003-0060), (2003-0092), and (2003-0104), 1 boxes
  Addition (2003-0060) (26 items, 0.4 lin. ft.; dated 1968-1998) includes chiefly issues of periodicals (1968-1995), and her calendars/appointment books (1981-1998).
  Addition (2003-0092) (2 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1939, 2000) comprises two programs, one, with ephemera inserted, for the 125th anniversary celebration of the Emma Willard anniversary celebration of the Emma Willard School in Troy, NY (October 6-8, 1939); the otherfor the Southern Association of Women Historians Fifth Southern Conference on Women's History, held June 15-17, 2000.
  Addition (2003-0104) (8 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1974-2002) consists of programs from the second (1974), third (1976), seventh (1987), and twelfth (2002) Berkshire Conferences on the History of Women.
- Accession (2003-0236), 9 boxes
  Addition (2003-0236) (2500 items, 4 lin. ft.; dated 1950-1999) consists primarily of Scott's personal and professional correspondence. Also includes subject files related to writing projects, lectures, research, and various professional organizations.
- Accession (2004-0330), 13 boxes
  Addition (2004-0330) (4300 items, 7.2 lin. ft.; dated 1932-2003 (bulk [1980s]-2002)) contains primarily correspondence, both personal and professional. Also includes writings and speeches by Scott and others; subject files; research files; and teaching materials, including student papers.
- Accessions (2007-0178) and (2007-0211), 2 boxes
  Additions (2007-0178 and 2007-0211) (700 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1951-2000) contain correspondence, research files, grant proposals, drafts and published writings including Teaching Parallel Lives, Virginia Women, and Georgia Women.
- Accession (2008-0236), 2 boxes
  Addition (2008-0236) (900 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; 1965-1995) includes correspondence, research files, and master's theses from students that Scott supervised at Duke. Also included are two boxes of 5.25" floppy disks.
  - Master's theses, 4 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Examples of devices for teaching American history (Box 1)
  - Correspondence in California at the Center for Advanced Study in Social Science, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Marnta Ragland (Box 1)
  - Creation of Sallie Bingham Center for women's papers (Box 1)
  - 5.25" Floppy disks, 21 disks (Box 1)
  - Texas Women (Box 2)
  - Greer diary (unpublished) (Box 2)
  - Data on Southern Women (Box 2)
  - Life of Virginia Gearhart Gray (longtime archivist at Duke) (Box 2)
  - Life of Julia Chevy Sprull (Box 2)
  - Life of Guion Griffis Johnson (Box 2)
  - Unheard Voices (Box 2)
  - Oscar Handlin Retirement Tribute (Box 2)
  - Eleanor Boatwright file (Box 2)
  - Unheard Voices: Data (Box 2)
  - Searching for Eleanor Boatwright (Data M.A.) (Box 2)
  - Muriel Beadle's History of Fortnights (Box 2)
  - Julia Flesch (Box 2)
- Accession (2009-0142), 2 boxes
  Addition (2009-0142) (900 items; 1.2 lin. ft.) includes correspondence, including a file of letters from Sacvan Berkovitch; Jane Addams subject files; files on awards, conferences, and remarks; League of Women Voters documents; Duke appointment materials; and essays and research on women's studies and women's history. Two files are restricted until 2010 and 2020.
  Arrangement note
  This accession has not been processed. Folder titles were created by the donor and have been transcribed into this finding aid.
  - Duke University Libraries, vol. 3, n. 1, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Sacvan Bercovitch, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - AHA award/OHA award (Box 1)
  - Transition from rural to urban society (Box 1)
  - Syllabi and notes: Slavery (Box 1)
  - Tell the South, Furman University, 1996 (Box 1)
  - UNC panel on co-eds (Box 1)
  - Southern ladies and some other (Box 1)
  - Letters from Dick and Jing(?) Lyman (Box 1)
  - Report on the provost (Philip Griffiths), 1987 (Box 1)
  - Advice to freshmen women, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Whose history are we talking about anyway? (Box 1)
  - Radcliffe conference, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Unclassified (Box 1)
  - Georgia women (Box 1)
  - France (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with historians, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Benjamin Franklin's sister (Box 1)
  - Origin of Women's Studies (Box 1)
  - A 1975 analysis (Box 1)
  - Duke appointment, 1961-1991 (Box 1)
  - Southern women after suffrage (Box 1)
  - Learning to write (Box 1)
  - Macaffrey(?) Lecture at Harvard (Box 1)
  - Political campaigns (Box 1)
  - Duke women: two lectures (Box 1)
  - Alternatives to Futility, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Mormon Women Other Women, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Letters from the 1940s and interview with James Reston (Box 2)
  - Looking Back from 1998: History of Duke (Box 2)
  - Harvard paper, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Taking issue (Box 2)
  - Graduate student concerns (Box 2)
  - Jane Addams documents (Box 2)
  - More Jane Addams (Box 2)
  - Thinking about Jane Addams (Box 2)
  - Writings from 1960s (Box 2)
  - Life of Guion Griffis Johnson (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1990 (Box 2)
  - Writing St. Janet and the Ward Boss (Box 2)
  - Memoir of Celestia Parrish, Georgia's Greatest Woman (Box 2)
  - Harvard newspapers (Box 2)
  - Judith Harlow Spearing (Box 2)
  - League of Women Voters rare documents, 1933-1995 (Box 2)
  - 2 files: closed until 2010 and 2020, respectively (Box 2)
- Accession (2011-0120), 1963-2009, 1 box
  Addition (2011-0120) (100 items; 0.3 lin. ft.) includes a file of Citizen's Advisory Council on the Status of Women, 1963-1977 and other research materials and a file on the National Women's History Museum.
  - Citizen's Advisory Council on the Status of Women, 1963-1977 and other research materials (Box 1)
  - National Women's History Museum info, 2009 (Box 1)